In this demonstration, we will look at how a model created in Knowledge Studio can be deployed along with seeing how code nodes can be used to generate code.
To begin first create a new workflow
Link over the Validation dataset and Decision Tree model.
Drag a Scoring node found under the Action palette, onto the workflow canvas
Connect the model and dataset
Double click the node to open the wizard
Set an appropriate target name and click next
Make sure the fields between your validation dataset and model are correctly mapped, then click next.
Adjust the cutoff values as needed, in this case we will use 0.7 and 0.3.
Select which fields to include, we're only interested in Customer ID for this demo.
Click run to generate the output.
Double click the output dataset to view results.
The report gives an overview for the scored results indicating the number of records scored as Yes and No depending on the cutoff values we set earlier.
From the data tab we can see the actual scored probability for each Customer ID.
Heading back to the canvas, lets generate the model in SQL code.
Drag the generate code node onto the canvas also found under the Action palette
Connect the model
Double click to open the wizard.
Set a target name and select SQL from Code Type dropdown. Note that Knowledge Studio supports a wide array of languages to export models in.
Click run
Double click the node to view the generated code for this predictive model
This code can be copied and used in other environments supporting the selected language.
By utilizing these 2 main methods of deployment, models can be deployed and used with ease.