In this demonstration, we will illustrate the Pivot Table node in Knowledge Studio.
To begin create a new workflow and link the census dataset.
Drag the Pivot Table node, found under the manipulate palette, onto the canvas.
Connect the census dataset.
Double click to open the Pivot node.
Set an appropriate name.
We will assign a variable one of 3 roles:
Pivot indicates a variable will be used as columns.
Group indicates a variable will be used as rows.
Selected indicates a variable will be aggregated based on Pivot and Group roles.
Let's select sex as our Pivot, and Response as our group.
Select age as our Selected, and use the average aggregation method.
Click run to generate the output.
Double click the output node and view the data tab.
We can see the aggregated result for age based on our selected Sex and Response variables.