In this demonstration, we will be exploring the strategy tree node in Knowledge Studio.
Strategy trees are slightly different from decision trees in the sense that they are used to help make business decision by running calculations on nodes and assigning treatments.
To begin we'll start from a new workflow with the Auto Grown decision tree model alongside Training and Validation datasets already linked.
Drag the Strategy Tree node found under the Model palette onto the canvas.
Connect the training dataset and double click to open the wizard
Here we can add calculations as expressions which will act as KPI's in our strategy tree. This can also be done in the strategy tree view which will be shown later.
Click run to generate the tree and double click to open.
By clicking options we can set various configurations for the tree.
Under the tree config tab you can adjust the orientation for the tree if needed.
Heading back to our tree view, right click on the root node and select find split.
You will be prompted to select a dependent variable, in this case we will use Response.
As can be seen, the relationship variable is selected to generate splits.
Right clicking on husband and wife node, then selecting find split.
If we select age as the dependent variable, it can be seen that values for age and response are shown in the selected node, but the splits only contain the new values from age.
This is because we selected age as the new decision variable.
Right clicking on the root node and selecting force split. We can select which variable to split by. Lets select education.
Create 5 bins by clicking on settings and setting number of bins then click ok.
Generating splits this way can be useful if you have previous business knowledge about customer segmentation and need to incorporate it into the strategy tree.
Lets add the KPI calculations mentioned earlier now, right click anywhere in the tree view and select calculations.
Click add to create an expression, for the first one we'll name it Profitability and get average of capital gain.
Add another expression, we'll name it Loyalty and get average number of products.
These expressions can be exported or imported in order to share with your team by using the import export buttons.
Lets export these expressions so we can use them in another model.
As can be seen on the tree, each node now calculates the Profitability and Loyalty.
Lets build out the tree a bit more using Response as our dependent variable.
Now if we want to see which segments have the highest KPI we can add color gradients to the tree by clicking options.
For node color source select gradient calculations and set mapped value to profit.
The lower number will get assigned white and the higher number will get assigned red.
Clicking ok, now we can see where the KPI is higher and where it is lower.
Next let's take a look at how we can assign treatments.
Right click on a node and select treatments.
Let's assign Mail to high KPI and No action to low KPI.
Now that we have treatments assigned, lets head back to the canvas and save the model instance.
Drag a new strategy tree and connect the auto grown decision tree model along side the training dataset.
By connecting a decision tree model alongside the training dataset, the strategy tree can use the decision tree as a base template.
Open and import the KPI's we exported earlier.
We'll also add a new expression for computed conditional treatment using helpers.
We are going to create 3 treatments
For capital-gain less than a average of 500, set treatment to No-Action. select "Add more treatments" after clicking next
For capital gain less than a average of 1500, set treatment to E-mail, select "Add more treatments" after clicking next once more.
For capital gain above a average of 1500, set treatment to Mail and review the code.
In the expression lets also setup a "and" clause to make sure E-mail is only assigned to greater than 500 and less than 1500.
Click ok and now the calculation is visible on each node.
To tell Knowledge Studio to treat this calculation as treatment, we can head over to tools and select "Treatment from calculations"
Select our treatment KPI and click run,
Now that each node has a treatment assigned to it, lets modify the tree colors to easily see which node got assigned to each treatment value.
Click options and set node color source to "treatments" to assign a color to each of the 3 treatment values.
Lets head back to the canvas and save the model instance.
Next lets use the scoring node found under the action palette to score the validation dataset with our decision tree model.
Drag the scoring node onto the canvas and connect the validation dataset and strategy tree model.
Double click to open the wizard
Set an appropriate name and click next
Make sure the fields are mapped correctly then click next
On the treatments page, null is used to indicate a node or record has no treatment assigned to it.
Next we can select which treatments and calculations to include in the output
Lastly select the output fields to include, in this case we only want customer ID.
Click run to generate the output
Opening the output dataset and viewing the data tab
We can see each customer id is now associated with a treatment.
The dataset chart can be used to see the percentage of records in each treatment.
Back on the canvas connect the model and validation dataset to a model validation node.
Validation for strategy tree adds a new heading to each node which indicates how the training dataset compares to the validation dataset.
Double click to open the wizard
Set an appropriate name and click next
Here we can select which calculations to include in the validation
The comparison mode page allows selecting how the comparison between training and validation should be made.
Click next and run.
Viewing the tree we can see that the validation heading has been added to every single node along side design and comparison.