The Binning block
At this stage all transactions have been merged, summarised and enriched with demographic detail but there may be a need to process the data further.
The data preparation group contains a block that can assist,  the Binning block.
The block is dragged onto the resulting dataset, connected, and double-clicked to access its configuration dialog.
The binning block can be used to create categories or bins for any variable.
The dialog has a number of areas.
First a variable to bin must be selected by moving it from the Unselected Variables list to the Selected Variables list, here tot_price_sum is chosen.
The binned variable is the variable that will be created and can be renamed.
Once selected there are four binning types to choose from: Optimal, Equal Width, Equal Height and Winsorised. Options for each can be set from Binning Preferences accessible by clicking the gears icons.
The Default bin count and Winsorrate values applies to Equal Height, Equal Width and Winsorised binning and the optimal Binning settings apply to the option Optimal.
Equal height binning attempts to create n equally populated bins, whereas equal width creates bins with the same width.
Winsorised binning removes a proportion of the largest and smallest values, here 20%, equal width bins are calculated and the removed observations are returned to the first and last bins respectively.
This ensures that the first and last bins are adequately populated.
Optimal binning settings include the ability to choose the measure, specify the starting and maximum number of bins to create, and deal with missing values. Also whether to force monotonicity.
There are also options to ensure resulting bins are adequate in terms of size.
The binning type "Optimal" requires selection of a Dependent variable and its treatment.
Here, there is interest in creating a new variable that re-cords whether total price sum is either low or high.
A good place to start is to choose Equal Height as the Binning type. From Binning Preferences, the default bin count is set to 2.
The Bin Variables button is clicked and this generates bins for the selected variable with bin cut points visible.
The Bin Statistics area relays the size and % of each bin in a frequency table. The view can be changed by hovering and selecting an appropriate icon.
Here, the icon "Show as frequency chart" is selected.
This view shows how the created bins are distributed across the variable "tot_ price_ sum". Bear in mind this is the variable that binning is based on.
The option to "Show as pie chart" is also available and bins can be isolated and compared by selecting them from the bins area.
From the Variable drop-down, DV is selected. Now the chart illustrates how the bins are distributed across the categories of DV. Changing the chart to a pie chart illustrates things more clearly.
As can be seen there is little difference across the DV categories in terms of the bin distributions.
The new variable is given the name: value_ bins,  and num_ products_ SUM selected.
The new variable to create is named to loyalty_bins and the Binning type selected is Equal Height, and the previous settings are retained and 2 bins are created.
The binning code for the transformations applied is available from the Binning Code tab in either SAS or SQL format.
The keyboard shortcut CTRL+S is used to apply binning settings and the asterisk disappears to reflect this.
Returning to the Workflow and opening the created dataset with the Data Profiler, the variables loyalty_bins and value_bins have been added.
Viewing the bins for each variable using charts, it can be seen that two bins are evident for each with an approximately equal number of observations in each bin.
Viewing the data, it can be seen that the bins have cutpoints that are not very appealing.
To address this, the binning code can be copied and used in a SAS Code block and applied to the data directly. This way the bin labels can be changed to something more readily identifiable.
The binning code is copied by selecting and using the keyboard shortcut CTRL+C. A SAS code block is selected and dragged onto the canvas and the dataset prior to the binning block is attached.
Double clicking opens the SAS Code block. First an output data set is needed, and this is added by clicking the "Add a new output dataset button" In the Outputs area.
The binning code copied previously is pasted using CTRL+V. Now, the bin labels can be easily changed . Here they are updated to low and high for each variable.
The code must be wrapped in a DATA STEP. This requires the use of the command "DATA".   This creates a dataset and this is dragged into the code and a semi-colon added.
Next, the data to process must be specified, this is done using "a SET statement."
The input dataset is dragged into the code and the code line is completed with a semi-colon.
Finally, a RUN Statement is required and this is added at the very end with a semi-colon.
Now the bin lables are changed.
Using CTRL+S applies the binning and the output dataset is created.
Accessing the new dataset via the Data Profiler and viewing charts for the created variables, shows labels have been applied and make the variable categories much easier to understand.
The binning can also be applied to other data by generating a binning model - this is accessed by right clicking the binning block.
Clicking the option configure outputs opens the binning block outputs dialog.
By default, a new dataset is generated, but this can be suppressed by moving it to the Unselected Output list.
Moving the binning model from the Unselected Output list to the Selected Output list and clicking OK, generates the binning model block.
The block cannot be viewed but now the binning can be applied to any appropriate dataset by connecting both the binning model and the dataset to bin to a Score block.
To illustrate, the same dataset is connected and the output is automatically generated.
Viewing the data, it can be seen that the new variables have been added.