To create custom blocks we will need to add a folder to our workflow properties
First create a new folder to keep our custom block workflows.
Next we need to set up our workflow properties to accept the custom block folder
Navigate to local, right click properties and select the workflow properties page.
Here click Add and select the new custom block folder we just created.
Our objective now is to build a workflow for a customer which will create a lag function.
First thing to do is create a new workflow inside our customer block area, we’ll call this "lag". Click finish.
Now we need to configure our workflow settings.
Click on workflow settings and select Custom block, found under the options page.
Give the block a name, select a icon if available and provide a description for the block.
Click apply and close to confirm.
Next drag the “Seasonal Sales” dataset onto the canvas.
Then drag a SAS Language block and dock it with the dataset.
Double click on the SAS language block and use the following code to allow the lag function to be implemented.
Create a new output so it corresponds with the code.
Press CTRL + S to save the changes and close this window.
Next we need to configure the parameters under workflow settings.
We will need to create two string parameters for this custom block, “by Variable” and “lag Variable”
Click Add to open the Create parameter dialog and create two parameters.
Click apply and close, doing so you will be prompted to configure the parameters.
For “by Variable” input Date and for “lag Variable” input Sales then click Apply.
Double clicking on the output dataset we can see it has outputted all rows as lagged values.
Next under Custom palette, drag the Output dataset block onto the canvas and dock it with the generated dataset.
Now save the workflow with CTRL + S, as we can see the lag custom block has been added under the Custom palette.
On a new workflow lets try using the Lag block we just created.
First drag the same “Seasonal Sales” dataset onto the canvas.
Next drag the Lag custom block onto the canvas and connect the imported dataset.
Double click the block to open the configuration dialog window.
For “by Variable” input Date and for “lag Variable” input Sales then click Apply and Close.
Double clicking on the output dataset we can see the lagged value has been applied as intended.