The Merge block can be used to merge all observations from both transactional files.
The Merge block is dragged onto the Workflow canvas. Notice the configuration status messages: Block requires at least two dataset inputs and: No merge operation selected.
The imported files are renamed to Jan and Feb respectively, and then connected to the join block and as a result
There is now only one configuration status message: No merge operation selected.
The Merge block is double-clicked to access its configuration dialog. Options are included to select the merge operation and a "By Variable".
Both connected datasets are listed and the available merge operations are: concatenate, interleave, and "one to one."
Concatenate stacks observations from one file on top of the other. Missing values may result if some variables that are present in only one file.
Interleave works on a observation index and requires a "by variable" as indicated by the error message.
One or more by variables can be included, and will result in an output dataset ordered by the by variable, in this instance ID.
The one-to-one option is based on observation row index and does not use a by variable.
The first file is used as a base, if there are additional variables in other file(s), they will be added.
Values used are taken by matching row index number.
The number of observations in the final file is equal to the number of observations in the smallest input dataset, here 1215.
Choosing to include excess rows will results in a file size equal to the largest connected dataset and some observations will have missing values.
The appropriate option to use here is concatenate, which does not require a by variable. OK is clicked and the process runs.
Opening the resulting dataset with the Data Profiler, it can be seen there are 3735 observations and four variables, as expected.
Viewing the data, 1215 January observations appear first, followed by 2520 February observations.