In this demonstration we’ll be going over the Text Transform block found under the Data Preparation palette.
To begin, first drag the “transaction V2” excel file onto the canvas.
Configure the block then click apply and close.
Double clicking on the dataset, we can see the number of observations are 3386 and this dataset has 11 variables.
We will be transforming the category variable, going to the charts tab and selecting category we can see all the category values displayed.
Let’s head back to our workflow and drag a Text Transform block onto the canvas.
Connect the dataset and double click to open the configuration.
First, we need to add an operation.
In input variable select our target variable “Category”
And for Output variable input a name to be used for the new variable.
Under Operation input “backslash percentage” to use it as our selector and select Regular Expression.
Looking at the preview we can see some 1’s, indicating this operation is working.
Now let’s go ahead and remove these symbols.
Clicking on the plus sign we can add a new operation.
From input variable select Category once more but this time keep the Output variable Category as well so we can overwrite it.
Under Operation select Remove and select Pattern for Remove.
For find use the same expression as previously.
As we can see in the preview the percentage signs have been removed
One thing to note is that while it seems alright right now, the names still have a whitespace at the start, it’s only the preview not displaying it.
To fix this, add a new operation.
Again, select Category for input and output.
Under operation select remove and from this time select whitespace.
Select leading whitespace, this will ensure the variables have no space at the start
Now if we look at the chart again, we can see that some values have upper case letters while others have lower case letters. We want to standardize that.
To do so first add a new operation, select the same variable.
Under operation select Change Case and select lower case. As we can see in preview now every value is lower case.
Going back to the chart we can also see there are some spelling errors.
Let’s create a new operation and once more select the same variables.
For operation select Replace, for Find, enter the incorrectly spelled word and for Replace, enter the correctly spelled word, “lighting.”
As the preview shows it’s been fixed.
Going back to the dataset we can see there are some categories that are very similar to one another and can be grouped together.
Add a new operation, with same variables. Select replace once more but this time for Find. input “DIY” with an asterisk which indicates finding all values that start with DIY.
For replace input the name we want to group them under, in this case just DIY.
Let’s do the same for the word “bath”.
Now if we save our text transform block with Ctrl + S and head back to the workflow. We can see here it’s run successfully, double clicking the output dataset and going to charts then selecting category.
We can see there are a lot fewer categories thanks the transform operations.