This demonstration goes over the Transpose block found under the data preparation palette.
We’re starting by importing 3 datasets for January, February and March followed by merging them into one dataset.
Looking at the dataset we can see there are some variables such as ID, number of products, total price and month.
Our goal is to display the total prices per month based on the unique ID.
For the merge block configuration, the operation is set to Concatenate.
As a result, we have a dataset will all 3 months.
Now drag a transpose block onto the canvas and connect the dataset.
Double click to open the configuration window.
First select the transpose type, we will select rows to columns.
In group by we will select ID, so each distinct customer ID we want the months transposed and display total price.
Under the transpose variables section, for Column ID, select Month. For variables select total price.
As we can see in the preview, the total prices per month are displayed for each unique ID.
Here we can change the prefix, let’s set it to “Price_”.
Once we’re done hit CTRL + S to save. Going back to the workflow and viewing the output dataset.
We can see the data has been successfully transformed as intended.