So in this top,
perhaps some decision tree,
we're just continue
working on the same path.
So what I'm going to do,
I store it with
the bagging model.
I've put a backing
on the canvas and
then boosting and
random forest.
Then I connect my
training dataset
to each of the.
I start with the
bagging model.
I can give it a name.
I'll just call
it tagging and
tells me what the
input dataset is.
Again, you can
have a base model.
In this case, I
don't have any.
Then I get to pick my
dependent variable.
And as you can see, I can
pick any types of
dependent variables,
numeric or excrete,
doesn't matter.
In this case, I chose on.
And for independent
variable,
I'm gonna do
a maybe capital gain
or you education.
I use hours per week.
Marital status
and relationships
and check so that
I just few of these
seven variable.
And then I click
next to where
I parameterize
my, my model.
So first thing From
the Top Model,
growth options,
number of trees.
So by default,
tougher have 150.
Please don't elect
to change it
to 50 because it's
going to take a while.
I'm actually going to
fuse 25 if you choose.
250, I'm going to take
five minutes to train.
You can pick a random seed.
For the sampling purpose.
If you don't want
that sampling
with replacement,
you can kind of
have this option.
But I'm not going
to turn that off.
I can also say,
if you want to reduce
your sample size.
So let's say, okay,
give me NH3 maybe
and 50 percent
direct or similar to
diffusion tree when you
grow a decision tree.
Again, so you have
the parameters are
for search method,
I keep cluster, and
then four measures,
I keep entropy value.
And at the bottom you see
the criteria or the
stopping criteria.
When building. Also grown.
It could be trees are going
to be gone automatically.
And I'm not going to
modify any of these.
And I'm just going
to click run.
The model, gets trained.
All right, not bad.
In the result.
When you open your model,
you just feed its
model overview tab.
That tells you what did
your DV and independent
My about yanking
out this time
into an attribute is just
setting of whatever
you had in
the width or your a
and your user
input with whom.
Nothing special.
So you don't
have any effort.
Similar to like let's say,
logistic regression.
You haven't feel a
distribution yet,
but that's a decision tree.
It got kind of
like a black box.
Could either just
so many trees.
We don't have anything
in early done.
What we can do is
dip at the end,
compare the performance
of the model.
The other technique.
Now let's go to the random
forests pain
source of Lindlar.
You just pick a name
for your model.
Then you select your
dependent variable.
And again, I'll
just shoot the
same variable, age, game,
maybe education
hours per week,
marital status and
relationships.
And nine.
And then for an
hour a week, 20 pi,
you get a number
of feature that
the percentage
of independent
liable to use
in each model,
in each tree, in each of
these 25 trees and
shampoo, a 50.
To keep the cluster
method for the,
for the third
method, entropy,
I'm not going to
change anytime you
usually don't
change any integer,
ie, I only worry about
number of tweet and
maybe number of feature.
And then I start
training boosting
tree, boosting model.
Okay, for the most
thing you will see,
I only have access to
binary variables are
dichotomous variable.
That one of the
shortcoming of pollution,
we can only use dichotomous
variable like
response PF and
no fraud or no fraud.
B11, I get to select
my target category.
Again, I use the same
set, our variable.
Hey, man here,
and I'll change the number
of, number of iteration.
We find after shrinkage,
shrinkage factor.
I'm not going to
change that to
keep it at 0.001.
I'm not going to
change anything else.
I just click on. Now
next thing I want to do,
I want to compare
the result of all
these models.
So what I need is
model validation
or of deeds.
I connect them model,
model validation
and connect
all the training data.
And then I go through
the model validation
step flow, agon validation.
I'll go through
the wizard and
not change anything
except Jeff F1 and
a cutoff because I want to
compare these
on-farm models with
my deficient we add and
I change the cutoff
to what I had in for
their decisions,
revalidation chamfer
and change it to
0.73, remove
this additional
column is correct.
I don't care about it.
Then I can expand
this from bagging.
And you see how
validation takes longer.
Have to go through
each record,
have to go to 25
decision tree
pretty today the
probability.
And then they
get average now.
And then the result gets
generated like lift
lower than random forest.
And the cutoff postwar
actually lower because
it has the FAD,
the sham out of
feature selection.
And now boosting
my title one.
I changed the cut-off 0.73,
like click on OK.
Now I take
model analyzer from
evaluate, collect.
All right, so I want to
compare the three models
also with the result
from Interactive be that
I have because I already
have the validated data
that from training data.
If you have the
validated data
that you can also grow,
you use that one.
But if I haven't done that,
then I just used it on.
So this data fact,
if the validated
data from this
interactively grown
efficiently using
the training data,
not the validation Mumbai.
And then I connect
the other dataset to
model and analyze them.
So now input tomato,
analyzer are or data.
Okay, We start
with the first one
which is coming from
the deficiency.
I make sure that I
choose yes probability
but yes category on
yes probability.
And I call this decision
tree interactive.
The next one is from
the bagging I choose.
Yes. And yes probability.
I'll call it bagging.
And random forest painting.
Yes, category
and the farm fields
probability.
And I renamed
the last thing
so we can see that
it can have a
longer if you have
a dataset with
the DV category and
the probability of
that, that PV category.
You can just really
didn't analyze that.
Even if the dataset
is your habit from before,
from somewhere from
different software,
you just need to bring it
in and do the comparison.
And I click Run.
So now, and now you
see that I have for
care the red one and
the decision tree,
which the performance
is lower than.
The other three.
The on-farm model,
the yellow if the boosting,
blue is bagging
and green in
random products like E3
are almost the same.
But you figure out
how they're doing
better than the fish entry?
I look at the
top 40 per fan.
They give me about 80
percent of the target,
85% of the target,
slightly higher than
auto grown three,
I believe it but 83.
Well, here I get 86.
Now I go to lift chart.
You can fit a bill
for the fame.
I should stop using them
or 40 percent of
my population.
And then ROC, I
look at the AU fee.
All right, and you see
for decision tree is 0.83,
while for lead or at
around point ADA,
it bagging 0.89
for random Firth
and 0.88 or boosting.
All right, Now how we
compare performance
of different models.
Mad, I find them useful,
like people use
them in like
customer retention,
churn fraud.
I can go to Action and I
say generate code and let's
say they give me
the Python code
for defy the
only 25 tweets.
But imagine that
you usually start
training for like
100, 150 tweets.
Imagine you need to
look at the rule
for a 150 trees.
If you've just 25 trees,
look at all the fluids and
byte array, guess
co-generation.
We didn't even
have these options
before we just added them
made a couple years ago.
So greeting you to at
least get the code and
put that into production.