So now we want to build
a PCA model or you
want to get some
principal components.
So let's create a new tab.
I'm just going
to call it PCA,
then I need datasets.
So we talked about that.
The main point of
using PCA is it's
just because we have
some correlated variables.
There are some
multicollinearity issues.
But instead of just like,
let's say removing
some of them,
I still want to
use those in some
of those informations
later in my model.
So instead of deleting
some of the variables
from the model,
I want to convert
them orally,
combine them to
generate new variables.
So go to the help menu
and there is this
per sample data.
Just click on that.
And then the
third sample data
is called credit.
All right, So what
knowledge is Studio
does it create
new project called
credit under
some already data on
pre-built workflow in it.
So what I need from
this workflow is just
these two data sets
training, not
even validation.
I just need the training.
I'm going to delete
this decision tree
because I don't need it.
So first thing
I want to do,
I'm first of all this
with a credit dataset.
So it's not
centered anymore
because for the
PCA, you only,
you can only use
numeric variables
to generate
principal component
does using
numeric values in
the census dataset does
not show any
multicollinearity.
So that's why I
want to use it.
Use a different
dataset to show
you when we face
a co-linearity.
Let's say when we build
regression models,
then I decide
to do some PCA.
Here is my training data,
and let's open it.
So I see that I have some,
I have 20 thousand
records with
29 variable under a
bunch of variables.
Let's say that I'm
already familiar
with my dataset and
I know which I want
to include in my logistic
regression model.
So I'm not going
to spend time
like exploring this data.
But let's also
see that, right?
I see some missing
values as well.
For example, in
this variable age I
have 2% missing values,
or let's say
years at address,
I see missing values or
let's say these
other variables,
they all have
missing values.
So I see some percentage
of missing in my data.
And for some of
the variables,
I'll just keep
that in mind.
Now I'm going to build
a logistic regression.
So I take a
logistic regression
from the modelling
pilot query is.
For the dependent variable,
there is a field
called the status
to please use that.
It has two categories
but death and okay.
So back that have the,
is the rare
category which I'm
going to use for
my prediction.
And I just keep
the variable selection
method under
must include all, all
selected variables.
So I'm not going
to use like
a stepwise or
other methods.
And then from this list,
see what I need to use.
First of all, I
sort them by name.
And then I'm going to use
a average monthly
balance, credit line,
recommended line, total
amount purchased,
total service
charge, revenue,
and years that address.
So these are the
variable that I want to
include in my modern age,
average monkey balance,
credit line,
recommend that line.
Transaction related
information and data.
And these are all numeric.
And I click Okay,
they all gets highlighted.
And then I can
use this icon,
the single arrow,
to put them in the
independent variables
selected area.
Okay, then click
Next and run.
Let's open the model.
And let's go to
the currently
selected sequence.
All right, now I
see that I see
some multicollinearity
issue by
looking at the VIF table.
I see, for example,
average monthly balance has
this seven number and I
also see total service
charge revenue, it's 6.9.
Also notice some of these
are not really significant.
You see the p-value,
although I've
got pretty high
entropy explained,
but this is not the model
that I'm going to use.
Based on the previous
information.
I would just go back and
remove one of
these variable.
But now that I
know what PCA is,
maybe I'll give it a
try and see if I can.
Instead of removing
these variables like
average monkey balance or
total service charge
revenue are all.
Try to see if I can
convert these into
some components and use
these two in my model.
All right, So for now,
I just leave this model
here and then I'm
going to build principal
component analysis.
So I drag out of the
training data and I go
to the model and I
choose principal
component analysis.
So again, all we see in
the available fields
are numeric fields.
If you open this
binocular icon,
you see the fish types
are all numeric.
All right, so
what a closer.
Again, I'm going to sort
these and I choose h,
average monthly
balance, credit line,
recommended line, total
amount purchased,
total service charge,
revenue, and years actress.
Once they are selected,
they gets highlighted.
And I put them
in the selected.
Now remember I talked
about the variance cutoff.
So if you want to
just give this,
if you want to include
and Phi all the components,
all the possible
components,
you can just change
it to a 100 percent.
But usually we
don't do that.
It's okay if you give me
just 70% of the variance
of all these variables,
I'm, I'm fine with it.
So the default is 70,
but you can always
increase if you want to.
Maybe I'll just increase it
first so you see what
the result would
be and then
I'll go back and
modify this.
All right, so
just click Run.
It's just one page.
All right, so eye opener.
First of all, I
get a warning that
these many records got
excluded because
of missing values.
And I know that this age
and I believe it was years
at address that I've
got some nulls.
So because correlation
cannot be generated,
then they've got excluded,
arose with the null value.
So that's fine.
Then I go and look
at the scree plot.
So scree plot tells me that
I have seven components.
Remember I have
seven variables
because I said give me the,
a 100 percent
variance is actually
gave me seven components.
But you see where
this eigenvalue
curve receiver,
it gets very cheap,
like it's right here.
Maybe I should only use
three to four components
because at this point,
if I look at the
cumulative percentage,
I see that I can get
the variance if I
just enough variance,
if I just look at the
first four components,
even if I look at the
first three components,
I get above 80 percent
of the cumulative variance.
But anyway, or I can
go back and modify
it later to actually
you see the red line.
It's, it's at the very end.
It's not a 100 percent.
So once you verify
that cutoff edges,
then you see a
line in the middle
wherever it breaks
that cutoff.
And then the next tabs
are eigenvectors.
So again, because I
have seven variables,
it gives me seven
eigenvectors
with associated
eigenvalues.
But by just looking at
this eigenvalue of
I can see that the
first two gives me
like if I add these two up,
it gets like 4.8.
And then if I say for
point a divided by 7,
it actually gives
us 68 percent
of information of
all these variables.
I can keep.
The third one is
close to one,
it's very close to one.
Since we say we are
interested in eigenvalues
greater than one,
because we expect
eigenvalue to give us
at least
information related
to one of the variables,
at least one unit
of variance.
Right away we see
that the other ones
has very small eigenvalues.
Look at.
The last one is just
wrecked nothing.
And then these are,
the last type is
just a component
coefficients.
So it tells me how the
coefficients also,
by looking at PC one,
I can see the years of
address is actually.
That's high impact.
Actually for most of them,
this one, same thing,
0.025 is the
coefficient for years
that address
also h is 0.02,
but Component number
three has the highest.
The value of
coefficients are higher.
Here is at address
0.09 and age is 0.03.
Anyway.
So in order if, if
I want to get rid of these,
fine, I can just
ignore them.
But for now, just to
see what happens,
I'll go back to this model.
Click Modify,
right-click modify,
and change this cutoff
to seven meters.
Okay?
So now I have
this a scree plot
telling me that
I should stop
at three components
because they
get more than 70
percent of variation.
You see that those
ones got disappeared.
The additional
one, again, 4567.
And then it's just
like a filter.
It gets disappeared
from the list.
How do I use this?
Let's close this.
I take a scoring node,
so I drag out of
this training data.
And then I go to
action and a scoring.
And with my PC, PCA model.
So I connect my data to
a scoring node and
the PCA model,
darling, I'm happy with it
includes three components.
Let's just give
it a short name.
So here you see that I
have the three components.
These are, these
components get
calculated and
will be added
to my dataset as a column.
So if I want to
exclude any of them,
let's imagine that I had
that 100 percent cutoff
and I had a list of
seven components.
I would just exclude
them here so many ways.
Just exclude them at
this point I can
modify the name.
So let's say if my
first component,
let's say it's related
to transactional
transactions.
I just give it
a related name.
Or let's say if my if my
PC number 2 related to,
let's say credit
line or like,
let's say the coefficient
for credit related
variables are like higher,
so I just give it
a better name.
And then PC number 3 carry
the information related to,
let say demographic I had.
Here's an address or age.
So I just call
it demographic.
So I can give each
component a new name.
So these are just
column names.
I can also export
these calculations,
so I can just click export.
And then in a
format would be
XML or plain text.
I just need to pick
a destination,
which this is the
credit project.
I prefer to keep it in
the same project and I
call it PCAs expressions.
All right, so
just save them.
If I want to edit any
of these calculations,
I can also do that.
So let's say you have
this business
rule and you want
to just change it or
modify anything here.
You can also do that.
And then down here I decide
which variables I want to
write in my output dataset.
If I'm not interested
in these additional
columns,
I can exclude them.
Let's say I don't want
this or this, or this.
I just want to keep
the other ones.
And I click Run.
All right, now, this
is my score dataset.
When I open it
in the report,
I get to see the
PCA expressions.
And everything else
is just similar
to what you've seen in
any other data set.
I noticed that if I
say calculate, all,
look at this piece,
PC principal components,
I see these missing values.
Remember that
I said age and
years are some
missing values.
So PCA was unable to
generate the associated
information for them,
So those rules
got excluded.
That's why in the PCA
I also see some
missing values.
The next thing I
want to look at,
I go to correlation.
And I only select,
let's say PCA and see
what you can see.
They're not
correlated at all.
So this is just a main
concept behind PCA.
So if I'm going to
use these in a model,
it won't cause any
multicollinearity issue.
All right, Now
I want to use
this in, in my model.
So how do I do that?
So right now in
this data set,
I already have PCAs,
but let's say you and I
use it in future for on a,
on a different dataset.
And you only if all
you need to keep
is actually those
expressions.
So you need to apply
variable transformation
to the data.
So drag out of the
training data.
Go to manipulate palette
and take a variable
transformation now.
So this dataset does
not have the PCA.
So I'm going to,
I already saved the
expressions for.
I'm going to import
them to click Import.
It's from an
expression file.
And then I referred to
where I saved them.
This XML file.
Once I click Next,
I get to see them.
If I want to exclude
any of them,
I can do that at the time.
Again, if I want to rename,
I can also do that.
And then those
three variables or
expression gets added to
my variable transformation
dataset editor.
And click Run.
Now I have the students.
I didn't want to use
this scoring data,
although it has the library
because the purpose
of scoring if different
than what we did here.
All right, and then
from here I'm
going to build
a logistic regression model
with three new variables.
So I'm going to
this model pilot.
I choose a logistic
regression model.
And I call this maybe PCA.
Greg. I choose status too,
and I'm interested in
but that category.
And then
all right,
I put them in the
selected area.
And then I run my model.
I'm going to
look at the VIF,
although we
already looked at
the correlation
matrix of the PCA,
this should also confirm
that you see all the values
of BIF there, R1.
And this is my final model.
But also look at the
entropy explain.
It. Dropped a lot.
But again, it's balanced.
Maybe this, these are not
the best components.
Maybe I need to
go back and bring
in more variables.
But technically the
goal is when you see
highly correlated
variables and
you don't want to
just delete them.
You go on try principal
component analysis
and see if that can help.
You also see the p-value
here is pretty high.
But anyway, it's
just a practice.
I also have generate code.
If I want to deploy this,
it's only SAS or Python.
Only two options.
It should probably just
generate
expressions for me.
These are the
three components
that I have, the
Python code.
This is how you build
principal component
and how your brand a
analysis node.