Okay, so when you
open your knowledge
is studio,
I should be able to see
something like this.
And again, you can
have multiple versions
on your machine.
Versions doesn't
really interfere.
I select Run, I go to
my homepage and I start
typing pork station.
You see I have
like two version
not to just do your work
as version 20.120
and then 2820.
Again, I always
recommend using
the latest version because
in the latest version,
prefix box and there
are always new and
it will feature.
So this is the
welcome page.
If you don't want
to see this page,
you can uncheck
this option.
Display this welcome
screen. Each time.
Anyway, I like to see
it because it shows me
my most recent working
directories that are used.
And on the left
side you see
your project pain.
And this is my
working directory.
To set your
working directory,
you'll go to File and
you set your
working directory.
Oranges hit Control
W. And here you
can just choose
wherever you want
to create your
working directory.
I've just created
folder called training.
So just continue working
in this directory.
I don't have any project
Let me just quickly
show you what is this.
So if I go to my
document and then I
go to this closure here,
that's my training folder.
So it's just simply
a fall live in a
working directory.
And now I'm going to start
creating a project does
how you can start
working and build
your workflow.
So I just go to File,
click Create,
project, or you can
just hit control and,
or you can just
click this icon,
this little icon,
the third one
in the toolbar.
And then you get a
pop-up saying that,
what do you want to
call this project?
You can choose any name
or you just use
the default name.
I just used the
default name
which is project one.
And I click okay.
So a project gets
created and at
the same time you
see now in
my working directory,
you'll be training.
I have this project one.
So it's just a folder.
Going to clubs.
Okay. I personally,
first thing I do,
I just turn on this greed.
I, I like it very much.
And then this is the
search menu on the top.
Let's say if I say
logistic regression
is just for,
once I start typing,
gives me this logistic
regression model.
And then once they selected
this pilot opens up,
the logistic regression
gets highlighted.
I can just place
it on my canvas.
You see that it's gray
and it's this dot is red.
It means they doesn't have
the requirement to be open.
So if I click on it,
I can't open it.
If I right-click on it.
I don't know how I don't
see any available option
except removing the
node or adding comment.
We just removed
n naught and
everytime we're gonna
remove nano together,
this popup
message reminding
you that if you're short
to remove the note,
because once you delete it,
it's gone, you can
bring it back.
First thing I want
to do, I want to
import a file so I
can use this file,
import, drag it,
and put on canvas.
The other option is that
I can right-click in
going through the
pilot or just
right-click anywhere
on the canvas.
And you see the
list of pilots.
Pilots or connect.
Profile is just,
you can go to the
menu and see what
you have available
and just selected.
So I can say File
Import and just
put that note on
the canvas and open
the viscera. For me.
The search is also
available here,
so I can just
click search and
this little search bar
appears on the canvas.
So I can just say File.
And then I see the
list here, phi import.
It shows me
everything with it.
Thevenin, anything
related to profile,
palette, it
shows up anyway.
Just pick File, Import,
ethnic shows up.
It opens up their
visit for me.
And again, if I need
help filling out
this result.
This result is pretty
straightforward and easy,
but in general,
you can just,
this is the thing
that I talked about.
You can just click Help.
It opens upon my
other screen and
then it shows me
the file import.
Health related, huh?
Okay. So let's just
import something.
So while I'm in this
file import menu,
you see the first thing you
can choose is
the file type.
I have bunch of file
types available.
You can import
from text or CSV,
Excel, KDD if
angles format data.
So let's say if
you already have
a different project
and you created
some data set and
that data set leaves
in the angles and you
haven't x lives in
the knowledge a studio
and you haven't
exported that data set
into a different format,
let's say text or Excel.
That dataset isn't
KDD form and you can
just import it into
a different project.
That's where you use KDD.
I'll show you how.
If you have any R
type or data type,
you can also
export those into.
Knowledge is studio.
Once it gets so important,
once it gets imported,
then turns into
a KDD data set.
Alright. And you can
import different
SAS type data
or SPSS from a species
native or portable.
I don't know what
the difference
between these two is,
but anyway,
these are the type of
files you can export.
Less juice, just text.
And then let's import,
let's say census dot TXT.
Or if you have
a CSV format.
We can also do that.
Let's just do a TXT.
Let's just import TXT.
Doesn't matter. All right.
I'm going to go through the
desert later for now.
I just want to, without
doing anything,
I just want to import
so I click run.
So now you see that this,
it used to be red dot,
now it turns into green.
And I have an output,
it's a green circle.
Any green circle
legacy on a workflow.
It, It's a dataset.
Okay? Any square node
is just a function,
like a function
either model
or a transformation.
But a green circles
are actually dataset.
Now, there are other things
in this connect pilot,
for example, dataset link.
If I want to, let's say,
create a second workflow
for doing data prep.
For example. I want to
use this census data.
So there are different
options to bring
this census data set
into this other tab.
I can choose or use
this dataset link.
So just put it
on the canvas
and just double-click
and I find the source.
Okay? And you see
that it just opens up
this project one exist
in the training
working directory.
And you see that I
talked about
this KDD format,
every data set, every green
circle in
knowledges studio.
If a k KDD format is
just an knowledges
stood your format data.
So if I want to
point into that
specific data,
so they just select this
KDD formats sensors
dot KDD, Catholic open.
So this is just a pointer
to where senses
dot KDD exits.
You don't make
multiple copies of
same data set,
just step pointer.
And you can also do
this with models.
So we have this model
link. So same thing.
So if you, let's
say you have
a decision tree in
a different project
and you want to
bring it into this project.
You can use these link No,
just to point to where
that model or
data set exist.
You can also bring
model from
external sources.
Let's say if you have
the PML model in
a PMMA format
or XML format,
as long as they
have that modelling
technique.
So if, if we don't have
that modelling technique in
knowledges stood,
you can't.
Imported. But let's
say if you have
logistic regression
in a PMO Mel format,
let's say we created
a logistic regression in R,
then converted it to PMMA.
You can bring it
into knowledge
is studio and
start using it.
If you have data
sitting on,
let's say your SQL
Server, I knew going up,
you want to pull it into
knowledge is studio.
We can use this
ODBC Import node
and then you can
start importing
data into knowledge
is studio,
that's about
connect palette and
this other thing like
import data set
from knowledge hop.
Again, I talked about
a knowledge hub is a
different software.
It's web-based, Let's
say in future if you
use knowledge hub and you
built some
dataset in there,
and you want to
just imported in
knowledge studio because
this is desktop.
Knowledge hop is
a web-based data
sitting is in clouds.
Do you want to import
it? You can use
this specific node
to bring data over.
And then the other thing,
the other function,
easy like is it
youth functionality
is imagine that you
don't wanna use this
link data set node,
but you already created
this new workflow which
is called data prep.
And now you want to put
a pointer to
this dataset on
this other workflow that's
called Data Prep can just
right-click and say link
on another workflow.
And then you
get a drop down
or whatever
workflow available.
In the project number one,
I only have one
workflow additional
For Data Prep,
right-click or pen.
You see that I have
another pointer to census.
This workflow will just
click link on
another workflow.
And I say data prep.
And now the second workflow
opens up and it
shows me that,
you know, as I said,
you can just comment.
But I can say this is
the census data and I
can say call it step one.
This is how you can
comment your workflow.
Now, wanting to be a very,
let's say, I want
to delete this.
Like I don't want
three copies
of sensors on
this workflow.
You just right click
and I say remove note.
It asks me if I'm
sure to delete it,
I can just click.
Yes, they get disappeared.
But if I check this option,
says delete the
underlying object
from the project explorer.
And if I check this,
they complete completely
remove sensors
from a project number
one so that KDD fine,
will be remove and
you get this warning.
If I click Yes.
That green circle
removes sensors now is
gray because it
points to this place,
which is census dot KDD,
but K sensors
that KDD doesn't
exist says fail
to find a source.
So make sure when you
are deleting data set,
if you don't want
and you want
to create a space
on your desk,
you check that option.
But you should be
very careful because
if you use data specific
datas at somewhere else,
let's say even in a
different project,
once you delete the
source, it's gone.
You see that here, it
becomes grey again.
Anyway. So that's
the thing to keep in
mind or ice the
let me just show you
this other thing.
You said that I,
if I just select
these two nodes
at the same time.
So I can select
bunch of notes
together than
a right-click.
You can delete them.
I can say remove nodes.
I can say make supernode.
That's what I just
showed you before.
These are just empty nodes.
I can give that
super node and name,
and I can just turn it
into a single node.
I'll put it aside.
Let's say if you
don't want to use
a part of your workflow,
but you don't want
I deleted you Ana,
keep it for later or
maybe go back
and look at it.
You can just do it this
way so it's cleaner.
But anyway, I'm going
to remove these nodes.
I don't want
them. All right,
so here is our step
one, importing sensors.