All the steps of
the wizard soap
a click modify
to just go back
to the wizard.
All the previous
settings already saved.
So I don't need to modify
the source file name
or target data set.
If you want to change
the target data
same, you can do so.
If you have any
specific encoding,
like your data has a
specific encoding to
follow a bunch
of them here.
Usually, auto detect
works very well.
I recommend to
always double check,
make sure that your data
looks fine after importing.
So when I click next
to the next page,
gives me an overview of
how my file looks like.
It's about, I don't know,
like top 20 rolls
or top 15 rolls
of their data.
Show it shows me the
file is delimited.
The first row if the title,
as it's already checked.
Knowledges studios
have the ability
to read fixed split phi.
So if you have
fixed bit files,
you can also import it
into knowledges do deal.
You can change
that a delimited,
This is again
auto detected,
but as I go to
the next page,
you see here it says comma.
Then you can change
the delimiter.
We have different top space
or if it's semicolon.
So if I change this to,
let's say semicolon,
you see how it looks like.
And then also for
the string makers.
So this file software
automatic detected it.
Double quoted string maker,
if you have no
string may cake and
just change it to
non or single quote.
So if you have
trouble reading a
file or you see,
you just see
something wierd,
let's say like there's
just try to change
their either delimiter or
the string maker to
just get the right format.
So I get a preview of
actuaries, top 18 roles.
I can see that I have
bunch of columns,
mostly demographic
information with
some additional information
like capital gain,
number of product,
capital loss.
And I click next
in this page, I,
I, I get to select
the variables.
So if there is any variable
you don't want to import,
you can just put
them in there,
not selected area which
is clicking them.
Or if you have
hundreds of columns.
And let's say here I have
everything in the
not selected area
under like so many columns.
You can always click
this binocular
and then sort the
columns by name.
And then a start
clicking what you need.
You just need to hold down
the Control key and
just select them.
And then once, say,
okay, they're highlighted.
And then you
can put them in
the selected area for
this demonstration.
I'll just keep everything.
I'm not gonna.
I'll just import
all the columns.
And then in the
next wizard,
I'll get the option.
I have several
option actually,
so I can change that
target type, data-type.
So for example,
for customer ID,
it's always recommended to
change that to a
string format or text.
So if I click on the Type,
I get a drop-down.
I can modify.
Well, let's say if you have
a data file and
you want to just
change it to a
specific format.
You can just do it to
this setTimeout
timestamp menu
and you get options
to modify things.
Then you see this
sampling on the top.
So if you are trying to,
let's say you're just doing
some exploration on
this data and you don't
want to import
everything into
knowledge is studio you
want to just import
the top thousand rows.
You can always pay
top and records
or a percentage of
records or just
number of rec,
or let's say I just want to
import 200 drug courts
randomly import 200 records
into knowledge is studio.
For this demonstration.
Again, I want to keep
all the records.
I'm importing everything.
If you want to.
Again, let us say if you
modify the type of data,
let's say a date.
You already have it as
timestamp and you want
to cut the time.
So only keep the
date portion of
that timestamp
variable, for example.
And you want to see if
you did it correctly.
You can always say show
data and then click
refresh and you get
a preview of what
you've done soul,
if you, you can see
the result technically
when you modify
the target type.
You also speak a column
called precision.
So if the value is 0,
it means that you want
to keep everything.
Let's say specific
lipid numeric columns.
If you want 13
decimal points,
let's say you have
ten decimal points
and you want to
just keep two
decimal points,
then you just change
it, let's say to,
to, to keep the
decimal part.
If you want to round to 13,
let's say around it to 200,
you just used a
negative number.
So just say, let's
say if you want
to round 278 to,
let's say show 300,
you just use minus two.
And then it rounded up
to the nearest 100th.
That's about precision.
Or just keep it at 0,
just to keep everything.
Because I, usually
when I import data,
I don't modify
anything first.
Because they want
to take a look
at my data as
raw as possible
first and then
I'll go back and
modify things.
Again. If you forget
to change any target type,
you can always go back to
this wizard and
changed the types.
And you also have
other options to change
the type of
variables later on.
So don't worry if
do you ever forget
to like modify things
or they import time.
It's just so easier.
And then I can click run.
So now I've
imported my data.
I'll just quickly
open it so you
can just double-click on,
on this green circle
to open the data,
we'll all just right-click
and open view.
And then you get this view.
I just wanted to see
if my customer IDs
actually string now
and I can confirm
that it was changed from
an numeric type
to string. Right.