Now, let's connect
the census data
to variable
transformation node.
And let's open the variable
transformation known.
We talked about this
missing percentage
of missing value column.
If I just click this,
it generates that for me.
I can see that I have
some missing values
in capital gain.
Now, if I want to,
let's say, add a field,
and let's say I want
to look our transform,
the capital gain,
just click Add Field.
And by default, it gives
this filled 15 name.
But I can just rename
it and I call it
like log capital gain.
Okay? And I don't know how
to do the log
transformations,
so I'll go to function.
When I click functions,
you see bunch of
functions, categories,
math, general
string, aggregate,
and so on to math function
that I'm looking for.
And there are a bunch
of them listed here.
And then I select,
for example, Locke.
All right, so when I
double-click on it,
it somehow gives me
the information.
So inside the bracket
you see it says
log transformation
accept a flow value
has to be numeric.
I can't log transform
the education
variable, for example.
But I want to do
capital gains.
So now I can,
if I already know
what the name of
the column is
with proper name,
I can just type it.
But if I don't,
I can always go to
this list of columns.
I just click on
this columns
here and shows me
the list of variables
I have in my data set.
And then I choose capital
K. Remember my cursor
was inside the brackets.
So when I click
this capital a,
it automatically
keeps back.
Maybe I say plus one.
And why is that?
Because they have
so many nulls in
capital gain log of null,
I don't get an erasure,
so I'll just say plus one.
So at least, sorry,
it should be
insight at this to
get the 0 value anyway.
And then I force data
to be instantiated.
So if I don't do
that, the lake in,
on this, the actual column
doesn't get created.
Only this formula is
going to be kd over
with my datasets.
So I always like
to force data to
be instantiated.
Again, it depends on how
much disk you
huh, available.
And then I click Validate,
it's okay, it works fine.
And I click OK, right?
So this is how I create
a new column to my dataset.
Now, let's say I
wanted to apply
this log transformation to
both capital gain
and capital loss,
but I don't wanna
do it twice.
What could I have done?
Could have done.
I could have
gotten to this
transform fields.
And here you see the
expression area.
It says selected fields,
so it applies
whatever expression
I want into.
A list of columns that a
select in the
selected area.
So I pick capital gain,
capital loss, put it
in the selected area.
By default, it
takes the name of
the actual column
and add the prefix
of x, PR,
underscore, tweet.
If you want to modify this,
please go ahead and do so.
You can, you can
either choose
prefixed are
actually suffix.
It can change the suffix,
prefix, whatever
works for you.
Again, I would like to say
cross theta to
be instantiated.
And then here I say, OK,
maybe do this, sorry,
log transform on both
of these files and
both of these columns.
Click validate.
It tells me that. Span it.
Click OK. And you see how
these two columns
got created.
So by just writing
one expression,
I applied the
same expression
into multiple columns.
That's about
transform field.
Let's go back to
this capital gain,
just log capital gain
or they created,
if I go back to edit field,
and let's say that
I want to use a
specific function,
but I don't know
what the syntax is.
There's this syntax help
bitches, hyperlink.
You can just click on it.
This Hayes shows you
all the syntaxes
that domain is.
So for example, if
you want to
modify a string,
you just click on
this a string.
It gives you all
the functions
we have available.
And let say you want
to apply our dream,
which is trim spaces
of specific texts
from the right side.
So remove their spaces.
So if I don't know
what the syntax is,
I go here or again,
I'll scroll all the
way to the top.
I'll go to general.
I don't know how to
write a case statement.
Case. And then here
I have an example to
see how the Syntax works.
Alright? So a lot of
functions are available.
Yeah, I never had issues
like finding something that
they need in here.
Mostly straightforward.
So here I created
these three variables.
Now, the other thing,
there's actually easy aside
from writing
expression myself,
let's say I click
this Add Field and I
want to create
a new variable
call relationship.
And I at number
two to it because
I want to create
a different
binning structure
for my variable
relationship.
And if I, if I already know
all the categories and
how I want to bin it,
I can just start writing
my cases statement.
But I am usually lazy.
I just go through
this helper menu,
click helper.
And the first option
and the most common.
Technique that we use
the spinning epic bidding.
Again, there are a
bunch of helpers here.
For example, generation
of dummy variables
or even this
lager transform.
You could objects
created at true here,
optimal binning power
transform substitute
missing values.
Creation of vague variable.
Anyway. So I go through
binning and you see
first it shows me
the continuous
valuable only if
like relationship.
It doesn't show
here because by
default the helper type
is continuous spinning.
But I'm looking for
a relationship which
is a category variable.
So I choose discrete.
I have the list of all
the string variables,
and I pick relationship,
and then I click next.
Again, I get this
popular range
editor window.
Now here I say OK,
I want to combine
husband and wife
and group them and
call them married.
And then I have
these other ones.
I group them and
call them Other.
And then the last one is
just itself on married.
I'm not going to touch it.
And I click and you
see how it creates
the quote for me.
So casement relationship in
husband and wife and
married and so on.
So it create, it generates
the code for me when
I click Finish,
already pasted in
my expression area.
And again, for theta
to be instantiated,
you don't need
to do duties.
I'm just used
to it so much.
And by the way, if you
want to look at data,
you can just kick
that showed a top,
bottom and then refresh
to make sure that
you've like this.
Like what do we get out
of this expression?
So tells me that the
first row becomes Other.
So you make sure
that you get what
you intended to.
Alright? So I say, okay,
and again here we
have the option
of data preview.
Again, you can
click always show
data, refresh.
And now it shows me
the entire data.
With data malleable.
That's about binning.
Let's do substitute
missing values.
So by again I add
field and then I
say capital gain missing.
Alright? And I go to help
her and I choose
substitute missing value.
I click next.
It says, select a
variable or rate.
I want capital gain.
What do you want to replace
the missing values with?
You want to replace
it with mean,
median mode, max means 0,
or you want to create
your custom expression.
I'm saying explain
custom value.
So if you want
to, let's say,
assign a code to whoever
capital gain is.
Let's say now you
want to serve,
now you want to
assign 9999.
You can do so. But
anyway, for this.
Case I, for this
demonstration,
I just take the mean.
And then you can
see that how it
creates the case
statement again,
when it's now, it
gives me the average.
Otherwise it just keeps
the original value.
So that's four bobsled,
two missing value.
So you can create that
vague variable here,
true helper options,
say my dataset.
Remember that I
didn't have equaled
portion on male and
female categories.
But my hope is
to create a wait
for that variable.
So my expression
type is weight.
And I say I choose
the effects variable.
And then this is the
proportions right
now, 33% versus 66%.
My geologist choose
the percentage.
Let's say if you
want to create
equal portions,
you just assign
50-50 percent weight
to each category and then
it generates the
number for me.
So for each record
with sex in female,
they get 1.51 versus
males that got almost 0.75.
And I'll just
call this weight.
Okay? And then I
click OK. Now I've
created a bunch of
new variables to my
existing dataset.
I click Run census one
as my output data.
No CDs are all my
new variables.
Or go to the Data tab,
let's just ignore
some of these.
These are my new
variables like
log transformation of
capital gain or
capital loss.
Relationship.
Number two, also,
this person,
customer ID number
four is husband.
But now I have
this new group.
I've put him, put them
under married capital gain,
like here is no,
but the capital
gain, this column,
I replace null with
the average of capital
gain in my dataset.
So every null, all of
the knowledge
replace with 1354.
And then this weight sex.
So how do I use
this weight?
This is my
original data set.
So I look at the sex or
go to Dataset chart.
I have 33% versus 66.
I'll just put
it on the site.
All right, now, if
I choose paychecks,
I see this thing is
just the frequency
again, similar.
Now on the top you
see there is this
weight option.
If I open the dropdown,
I see the list of all
numeric values in my data.
I choose weight sex.
Now, I go back to
my x variable and you
see what happens.
So it applies the weight
to my entire data set.
Now when I look at that
specific variable,
I can CDs qual portion.
And then there's this way
toggle that is on,
on my datasets.
So even I, if I
close the dataset,
that way toggle remains on.
It's in opposite with
filter toggle
cause for filter,
when you're, when
you close a dataset,
it turns off automatically.
Next time you open it,
you want to make sure that
turns on the filter.
If you're planning to
look at the filter,
DID about four
weight, it remains.
And the reason is that
if you use a weight,
especially when you
technically for modeling
and you feed a modeling
node with data set,
then that modelling
nor knows that
this dataset is weighted
and then use it.
So that's the whole point
of having this toggle.
So if you want to,
if you turn it
on the modeling node,
nodes automatically,
otherwise like even
if you turn it off,
you can still go
manually inside
the modern Romania Liao
and apply the
weight valuable.
But this is just to
show you how to create
weight variable using
variable transformation.