This data set is the
one that I created,
the different drived
variable instance.
Number one.
What do I want to do is to
create different Sam
first think I want to
create is to create
validation and
training dataset
using partition node.
And I want to go to
the a random some funding.
So input as this
census number
one and I start
adding partition.
So I say OK at
one partition and I
call it training.
Going. Use this part,
this partition for
training purpose.
And I assign 70% of
my records to this dataset.
You can also choose
record count if you
know how many
records you want to
assign to training
partition.
I also add in
another partition.
Then validation is
the other partition
I want to create an
ISI, the other 30%.
And by the way
you see there's
this cylinder that
gets updated based
on what percentage
of data was
you flow training
I assigned 70%.
It's been colored red.
Means this is
already youth.
I only have this much
available. So I say 30.
And then let's say if I,
if I just say 20 and
then our update this,
it still shows me how
many what percentage
of record has left.
Once it gets deactivated?
If you click on it,
it gets activated again.
So I'll just change
it to 30% Update.
And by the way, you always
can go to this
preview tower
tells you actually how
many records
will be assigned
to this two partitions.
If you just,
you want to see
how many records are
in each data set.
Or you can also
assign random seed is
just too if you want
to generate the
same partition
every time you rerun
this partition node,
you can just
keep the same C
And that's about it.
Go, the output of
my partition node
is two dataset.
The first one,
this validation,
has 4,884 record,
which I'm going to
use when I want to
validate my
model in future.
And then the training has
about 11 thousand records.
So I can also
use partition,
not for another purpose,
flow, the filter Note
that we currently
have, it's a new node.
We didn't have that before.
So I used to use
this stratified
function here to just
filter my data or
so let say if I
say I want a stratified
partitioning,
I start adding.
And I say, okay,
based on education,
I want to create
three different
dataset. All right?
And I don't have the option
of defining expression.
I can just see all the
categories and how,
what do I want from
each category?
So first of all, I want to
create a category called,
let's say, people with
no high school degree.
So I should probably assign
all the records
from tenth grade,
maybe 11th grade,
from first to 4,
fifth grade to
sixth grade, 176.
And then all of these
records and then all
of these I'm going to
keep this preschool 32.
All right. So that's
my first partition.
People with no high
school degree,
I create a data set
and call it noise.
Then I create another one,
and I call it high school.
So you see that all
these other grades,
the available
records becomes 0.
So I don't have
access to them.
How come I missed a
lev and just do this?
Because they missed 11 in
the previous Oh, yeah.
637. Just copied
the same number.
All right. People with
high school degree
or grade 12?
Maybe they assign
these other ones.
Associate Academic slow CA,
79 high school, grads, WOW,
5,283 professional
schools, and 35.
A step. These
are people with
high school degrees I
created or not dataset.
And then the last one,
I want to keep people with
university degrees
in the same dataset.
Cuz I want to do different
analysis on each
of these K, 934.
Okay? Now if I
update the cylinder,
see now I have
three groups.
Use all data.
If I want to look at
number of records,
I can open this preview.
And it tells me in
each partition how
many records I have.
No high school.
1931 high school, 10,565
and the university.
Okay, I can close this out.
I get three different
data sets. Some output.
Take unordered
partition, not again,
again, using
this a stratify,
if I want to create
a dataset with
equal number of records
for males and females.
So I pick the filled sex
and it shows me
the available
number of records.
So the maximum, maybe I
just take 5
thousand of each.
Right? And I call
it equal sex,
and I run it.
Now, I've got the
subset of census data
which go to this
dataset charts on sex,
I can say I have 5 thousand
records on female and
5 thousand records on made.
So that was
another example.
Stratified sample Des
Moines I showed you.
And that's about it
says everything about
partitioning, random
versus stratified.